Guide to the Cyrus Adler Papers (includes Shorewalkers) 1952-2011 MS 3
New-York Historical Society
Cyrus Adler Papers
1952-2011
New-York Historical Society
MS 3
8.25 Linear feet ( 17 boxes, 2 flat files)
This collection contains records relating to Cyrus Adler's involvement with New York City political and community organizations between 1952 and 2011. Adler, a long-time resident of Manhattan's upper west side, founded Shorewalkers, Inc., in 1982 to preserve and protect the Hudson River waterfront, and the largest portion of the collection relates to that organization. Among the other organizations represented are the 97th Street Block Association, Village Independent Democrats, Broadway Independent Democrats, and Scientists and Engineers for Kennedy and other candidates.
Biographical / Historical
Cyrus Adler was born in Brooklyn in 1927, and for many years taught oceanography, physics, and math at City College of New York, Long Island University, and other educational institutions. A long time resident of Manhattan's upper west side, Adler has since the 1950's been very involved in community and political organizations. He played a leading role in the West 97th/98th Street Block Association and their efforts to transform a defunct restroom into a community and information center. In addition, Adler was active in many New York-based democratic polical organizations, such as the Riverside Democrats and the Stevensonian Democratic Club.. Adler also played a role in various transporation initiatives in the 1970's and 1980's, advocating for projects like the Westway Highway Tunnel and Central Park Toll Tunnel to move vehicular traffic underground and create more park space for the public.
In 1982, Adler founded Shorewalkers, Inc., a not-for-profit organization founded to promote greater access to New York's waterfront, encourage shore walking, and advance preservation and enhancement of metropolitan shorelines. At the time, large portions of the New York-New Jersey shoreline were inaccessible and/or lined with trash and rubble. As the urban shipping industry declined, abandoned piers were inhabited by homeless people and drug dealers. By organizing hikes and excursions along waterfront areas throughout the metropolitan region, Shorewalkers helped spur their transformation into parks and greenways. In particular, their efforts contributed to the creation of the Hudson River Greenway, the 11-mile route from Battery Park to the George Washington Bridge. Adler has written several books, and numerous articles and reviews.
Arrangement
This collection is organized by subject into five series: 1. Political Organizations 2. Community Organizations 3. Transportation Initiatives 4. Shorewalkers 5. Peace Movement.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers. Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Items that include presidential signatures will be presented to researchers in duplicate form.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Scope and Contents
The materials in this collection document Cyrus Adler's involvement with political and environmental organizations in New York, and with various transportation initiatives, such as the Westway Highway and Central Park Toll Tunnel. The materials span the time period from the 1950s to 2011, and include fliers, news clippings, and correspondence. The bulk of the collection concerns Shorewalkers, Inc., a non-profit organization Adler founded in 1982 to clean up and make publicly accessible the many waterfronts surrounding New York City, particularly the Hudson River waterfront.
Urban transportation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Waterfronts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Democratic Party (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Political Organizations, 1952-1987
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of fliers, news clippings, newsletters, and other materials from the various democratic political organizations that Adler was affiliated with from the 1950s through the 1970s. Among these groups were Scientists and Engineers for Kennedy, Carter and McGovern, respectively; Village Independent Democrats; the Morningside Gardens Democratic Club; and Riverside Democrats.
  - Adler's applications for membership to various organizations (includes biographical information), 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alabama Christian Movement for Human Rights, 1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Includes multiple issues of The Southern Patriot, a publication of the Southern Conference Education Fund, Inc., which reported on the Civil Rights movement in the South.
  - Broadway Independent Democrats, 1959-1961 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee of New York Independent Democratic Groups; New York Democratic Study Group; and related groups, 1956-1960 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4-5)
    Includes documents from umbrella organizations, including the Democratic Study Group, which consisted of members from each of the ten Democratic clubs in existence at this time. Also includes documents from assorted local Democratic clubs. Of note is a c. 1956 map of Manhattan's New York County Districts broken into Assembly Districts. Other materials include correspondence to representatives, news clippings, campaign newsletters, and a newsletter of the Council of New York Democrats that lists the various clubs and their respective current news.
  - Committee to Re-Elect William F. Ryan to Congress, 1961-1962 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - F.D.R. Woodrow Wilson Democratic Club, 1981-1987 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes lists of names of elected district leaders, board members, and delegates of the 69th Assembly District of 1982.
  - Morningside Gardens Democratic Club; Truman Democratic Club, 1959-1963 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - News clippings (includes draft of Adler's article, Politics on the Harlem Border), 1957-1963 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Reform Democrats, 1961-1963 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    Materials on the Fort Washington -Manhattanville Reform Democrats
  - Riverside Democrats, 1958-1977 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-4)
    These folders contain minutes, newsletters, membership notices, and other materials relating to the Riverside Democrats-Seventh Assembly District.
  - Scientists and Engineers for Carter, 1976 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scientists and Engineers for Kennedy, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6-7)
    Includes a 11/7/1960 letter sent to members highlighting the record of Senator John F. Kennedy on Space and Science; a Biltmore Hotel Directory for the Democratic State Committee Campaign Headquarters; and a letter on White House stationary from the President's special assistant.
  - Scientists and Engineers for McCarthy, 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Scientists and Engineers for McGovern, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Scientist's Committees, 1968-1972 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    This folder contains correspondence and progress reports on several scientific societies and committees.
  - Stevensonian Democratic Club, 1952-1960 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2-6)
    Includes minutes, news clippings, and election campaign fliers. In addition to Adlai Stevenson, candidates represented include Dr. Martin B. Dworkis, Gertrude H. Kessner, Robert F. Wagner, Carmine de Sapio, William F. O' Connor, Sidney Moses, Paula R. Berger, Virginia Dwyer, and Shanley Egeth.
  - Village Independent Democrats, 1956-1959 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7-8)
    Includes brochures, member information, and history of the Lexington Democratic club; its structure, platform, and achievements. Also includes a booklet "What the Well-Informed Village Independent Democrat Should Know."
  - Village Independent Democrats Newsletters; Articles on Richard Nixon, 1955-1960 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9-10)
    Folder includes political journals Straight from the Shoulde r from 1955 and Democratic Digest from 1958.
- Series II: Community Organizations, 1958-1984
  This series contains fliers, bulletins, minutes, correspondence, and photos from several Upper West Side community organizations with which Adler was affiliated. The bulk of the materials relate to the 97th Street Block Association. Adler served as President and coordinator of the Association during the 1970s and 1980s, and he and other members converted an abandonded comfort station into a neighborhood safety and information center called the West Flank Safety and Information Center (WFSIC). When completed, the community center provided area residents a first aid station and recreation center, and ultimately helped revitalize the community by reducing crime. Several letters from Adler discuss the challenges in working with the Broadway Mall Association (BMA) to transform the comfort station into the information center. The materials document the evolution of the comfort station into the community center.
  - Citizens for a Quieter, Cleaner West Side, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Federation of West Side Block Associations, 1979 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - West 97/98th Street Block Association, 1976-1984 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3-11)
    Folders include a variety of material, such as fliers and minutes on the efforts to revitalize the Boomis-Chemical Bank Building; a bulletin from 1977 to members discussing the pending demolition of the 'Boomis-Chemical Bank Plaza"; news clippings on complaints by various community groups and the negative impact of Single Room Occupancy hotels (S.R.O.) on the community and efforts to clean them up; photos of the unused bathroom/comfort station on 97th and Broadway; and a 1980 permit from New York's Department of Parks and Recreation granting permission for the Broadway Mall Association to clean and refurbish the comfort station on the Broadway Mall between 96th and 97th streets.
  - Miscellaneous, 1974-1995 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
    This folder contains the following materials: New York State Council on the Arts Cultural Services Agreement from 1974; a Lenape Trail Agreement between Public Service Electric and Gas Company and County of Essex from 1982; a 1994 COSMEP Buyers Listing and Catalogue from the American Booksellers and American Library Association conventions. Lastly, a public notice regarding a public meeting on the status of the Manhattan East Side Alternatives (MESA) Study hosted by the Metropolitan Transportation Authority and New York Metropolitan Transportation Council.
- Series III: Transportation Initiatives, 1973-1999
  This series contains fliers, correspondence, news clippings, and other materials about the various transportation initiatives Adler took part in during the late decades of the 20th century. The bulk of the materials pertain to the Westway Highway Tunnel Project during the 1970s and 1980s. Developed by Governor Rockefeller's Urban Development Corp., the Westway Plan gained support after a section of the West Side Highway (WSH) collapsed in 1973. This massive project called for new landfill to extend 1,000 feet into the river, a sunken two-tiered highway, parks, and new real estate development. Many New Yorkers supported this plan, including Adler, who argued that this new highway would be used by trucks and cars, eliminate pollution, transform the waterfront, and act as a catalyst for the redevelopment of the West Side. The Westway received approval from both city and the Federal government, but the proposal was rejected in 1985 due to environmental issues. The various documents included in this series capture both the supporting and opposing viewpoints of the project and what led to its demise.
  Among the various organizations that Mr. Adler was involved with to promote the Westway Highway was the Scientists' Committee for Public Information, Inc. (SCPI). Founded in 1958, SCPI was an organization of scientists, physicians, and engineers whose purpose was to objectively evaluate technical issues of a project that would allow the public to make informed decisions. The SCPI's Transportation subcommittee acted as coordinator for several teams of experts who examined the various subsections of the West Side Highway Project Environmental Impact Statement. Also included are materials on two subsequent proposals to restore the West Side Highway: the Route 9A Reconstruction Project and the Miller Highway Project.
  There is also a small amount of material on Adler's efforts to improve bus service and the Central Park Toll Tunnel.
  - Subseries III.1: Westway Tunnel Project
    - Westway Fact Book, 1977 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
      This booklet contains a comprehensive background and chronology of the Westway Project.
    - Council on the Environment, 1974 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
      This folder contains several environmental fact sheets and reports, many if which are annotated. Of note is "The Energy Impact of West Side Highway Alternatives," a statement read beore the West Side Highway Project Public Hearing on September 12, 1974.
    - Scientists' Committee for Public Information, Inc. (SCPI), 1973-1976 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3-4)
      These folders contains correspondence, reports, and newsletters on the environmental impact of the Westway Highway as determined by the Scientists' Committee for Public Information, Inc. Includes materials from special interest groups.
    - SCPI Land Use Task Force, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
      Of note is the booklet, "Land Use and the West Side Highway Recommendations" from the Transportation Administration of New York and City Planning Commission.
    - Westway Coalition Correspondence, 1973-1980 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
      Includes correspondence to and from government officials including Mayor Ed Koch, the Parks Council, and the Department of Transportation. Of note is a letter to the Editor of Our Town regarding a political cartoon on the Westway Highway dated March 18, 1978.
    - Westway Tunnel Coalition, 1972-1979 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7-12)
      These folders consist of correspondence, city planning materials, news clippings, and newsletters about the Westway Tunnel Project. Includes a Department of City Planning Publications and Information Guide, as well as a list of transportation experts who testified at a Manhattan Auto Hearing.
      Includes financial highlights for NYC Transit System for fiscal years 1969-1970 and 1975-1976, correspondence to the following: the Federal Highway Administrator regarding the distribution of federal highway funds and the United States Environmental Protection Agency. Also includes a statement by Congressional Representative Bella S. Abzug.
      Includes pros and cons to building the highway captured in news clippings and newsletters. Also includes minutes from a press conference given by the coalition.
    - Westway Tunnel Coalition, 1972-1979 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Westway Tunnel Highway Study Group, 1976-1978 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
      Includes correspondence from the public supporting the Westway Highway.
    - Westway Tunnel Highway Project-- Opposition To, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
      This folder contains press releases and other materials from various committees and organizations opposed to the project, including the Coalition Against the Westide Expressway.
    - Westway Tunnel Highway and Brooklyn Bridge, 1975-1984 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5-6)
      This folder contains the article, "Westway and the Brooklyn Bridge," as well as correspondence relating to the article.
    - Westway Draft Environmental Impact Statement, 1974 April 25 (Box 6A, Folder unknown container)
    - Westway Final Environmental Impact Statement, 1974 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
    - Westway Environmental Impact Statement: Section 6, 1974 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
      Provides comments and responses on the Drat Environmental Impact Statement and includes a list of the agencies, organizations, and private ctizens who commented on the West Side Highway Project's Draft statement.
    - Westway Highway Project- Demise, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
      Includes news clippings on Westway setbacks, as well as articles by Cy Adler on how the demise of the project would hurt New York.
  - Subseries III.2: Miller Highway Project
    - Miller Highway Project Draft Environmental Impact Statement-Executive Summary, 1999 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)
    - Miller Highway Project Draft Environmental Impact Statement Volume 1, 1999 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
    - Miller Highway Project Draft Environmental Impact Statement Volume 2, 1999 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
  - Subseries III.3: Route 9A Reconstruction Project
    - Route 9A Reconstruction Project Draft Environmental Impact Statement Appendix C Cultural Resources, 1993-1994 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
    - Route 9A Reconstruction Project Final Environmental Impact Statement Appendix C Cultural Resources, 1994 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
    - Route 9A Reconstruction Project Draft Environmental Impact Statement Appendix F Pedestrians and Bicyclists, 1994 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
    - Route 9A Reconstruction Project Draft Environmental Impact Statement Appendix I Coastal Zone Management, 1993 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
      This folder also contains Projected Accident Rates.
  - Subseries III.4: Other Transportation Initiatives
    - Improving Bus Service, 1958-1959 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
      Folder contains correspondence to and from Representative Daniel Kelly to improve bus service in New York.
    - Traffic Quarterly: An Independent Journal for Better Traffic, 1977 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
      This journal, published by Eno Foundation for Transportation, Inc., discusses the energy crisis and transportation issues such as ride-sharing services and urban transportation. Of note is a letter written by Mr. Adler to Wilber S. Smith, Chairman of the Eno Foundation.
    - Central Park Toll Tunnel, 1989-2002 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
      This folder contains correspondence, fliers, and articles about a proposal to build a tunnel under Central Park between 59th and 125th streets. Mr. Adler was the Director of the Vehicular Urban Toll Tunnels (VUTTS) Consortium, which promoted digging tunnels under the city for vehicular traffic to reduce pollution and noise.
- Series IV: Shorewalkers, 1968-2011
  Historical Note
  Shorewalkers, Inc. was founded in 1982 by Cyrus Adler and other environmentalists to explore the entire waterfront and shore trails in the New York Metropolitan area. Shorewalkers' mission is to explore, enhance, enjoy, and protect the parks, promenades, and paths along the waters in and around the greater New York metropolitan region. Shorewalkers' first hike took place Sunday, December 12, 1982 along the west coast of Manhattan. Their announcement read: "Explore the changing Hudson River Coast, Battery Park, the Westway Route, active piers, through Penn-Central railroad yards and into Riverside Park. Lunch stop in Harlem. Wilderness above the George Washington Bridge, wind up in an Irish pub in Inwood." They ventured along Manhattan's waterfront at a time when the Manhattan waterfront greenway was not a accessible as it is today. Since 1982, thousands of people have explored the New York, Newark, and Jamaica Bays; the Hudson, Bronx, Hackensack, and Passaic Rivers; the Gowanus, Newtown, and other inlets; the Croton Aqueduct; the Long Island Sound, and Atlantic Ocean among other waterways. Among their most well known walks are The Great Saunter, an annual all day hike along Manhattan's 32-mile shoreline, and the annual Walk off the Turkey (WOTT), a post-Thanksgiving Day hike. Shorewalkers' continues to promote the Hudson River Shore Trail, a 56-mile trail along the Hudson River up through New York state ending at Bear Mountain, known as the "Batt to Bear Trail." The Shorewalkers' efforts to preserve the Hudson River shoreline contributed to the creation of the Waterfront Greenway enjoyed by New Yorker's today. Among the organization's many supporters was the folk singer Pete Seeger, who wrote the lyrics for the Shorewalkers' Saunter.
  This series contains Adler's administrative files for Shorewalkers, Inc. Materials include mission statements, minutes, records of annual meetings, newsletters, press coverage, correspondence, financial reports, fliers, certificates, member lists, and sign up sheets. In addition to documenting the growth of this particular organization, these materials relate to broader topics such as city planning, environmental issues, health, recreation, and clubs and organizations.
  This series also contains photographs taken on many walks during the 1980s and 1990s. The photos document the various locations in and around New York that Shorewalkers members walked including: lower Manhattan, Central Park, Harlem, the West Side HIghway, Washington Heights and Inwood, the South Bronx, Coney Island, Red Hook, Far Rockway Bungalows, Bay Ridge, Jamaica Bay, and bridges. The photos also captured walks along the Hudson River Shore Trail with places such as Croton Creek, West Point, the Albany River, Bear Mountain, Newburgh, Storm King State Park, Cold Spring, and Poughkeepsie, NY. Many photos, particularly those of the Hudson River waterfront, document what the areas looked like before development.
  - Subseries IV.1: Administrative and correspondence
    - Administration and Planning, 1984-1985, 2004 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
      This folder contains the organization's Certificate of Incorporation, Bylaws, mission statement, and related materials. Also includes a document titled "Shorewalker Cabinet #1," an alphabetical list of Adler's files as of 2005.
    - Directors Meeting Minutes, 1985-1991 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
    - Directors Meeting Minutes, 1992-1994 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 5)
    - Directors Meeting Minutes, 1995-1999 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
    - Directors Meeting Minutes, 2005-2006 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7)
    - Directors and Board Members (includes Nominating Committee), 1985-2005 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 8)
    - Annual Meetings and Reports, 1987-1989 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
    - Annual Meetings, 1990-1994 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 10)
    - Annual Meetings, 1995-1998 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 11)
      Of note is a list of members and dues paid, as well as several financial statements.
    - Annual Meetings, 2000-2003 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 12)
    - Annual Meetings, 2004-2005 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 13)
      This folder includes financial statements and member surveys.
    - Shorewalkers Correspondence to Politicians, 1976-1990 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
      This folder contains correspondence about environmental issues from Cy Adler to the following politicians: Presidential candidate Michael Dukakis, Mayor Ed Koch, and Mayor David Dinkins.
    - Membership Renewal Notices, 1998-1992 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2)
  - Subseries IV.2: Newsletters and Press Releases
    - Awards and Citations, 1992-2005 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3)
    - The Shorewalker Newsletters and Calendars, 1985-1994 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4)
    - The ShoreWalker Newsletter, 1994-2000 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)
      The ShoreWalker was published seasonally and listed the upcoming hiking schedule, events, and announcements.
    - The ShoreWalker Newsletter, 2001-2006, 2011 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)